[Music playing]
[graphic of logo: USGS, science for a changing
world]
Yes!
Yellowstone is a volcano
An unscripted interview, January 2009, 7:00
Minutes
[video of geologist standing in front of a
large geologic map of Yellowstone while he
talks to the camera and points out features
on the map]
Yes, Yellowstone is a volcano.
My name is Jake Lowenstern and I work for
the U.S.
Geological Survey.
I'm the Scientist-in-Charge of the Yellowstone
Volcano Observatory
and that's a partnership with the USGS, the
University of Utah who does the actual
monitoring of the earthquakes and ground movement,
and the land manager Yellowstone
National Park.
[logos of three agencies in the corner]
How do we know that Yellowstone is a volcano?
We're looking here at a Geologic map of Yellowstone
National Park and the different
colors represent different geologic units,
different rock types, different ages of rocks.
You can see that all of the pink units in
here, these represent the youngest lava flows
mostly that erupted at the Yellowstone volcano.
[1:00 minutes] Most of these are between
about160 and 70,000 years old.
And we see that they're covering up this area
of the park.
It turns out this is the Yellowstone caldera.
It starts around here and it moves out into
the
area over here and it is about 50 miles long
and it formed when this green material
erupted.
This is called the Lava Creek Tuff and the
age of this unit is found here in the
light green and dark green, also to the south.
The age is 640,000 years.
This was an
enormous eruption and it spread ash over much
of the United States [graphic showing
map of US with ash spread from offshore LA
to offshore Louisiana to nearly Illinois,
and
into Canada] and a similar eruption to that
today would certainly be a big deal.
But since
this time, there have been about 80 different
eruptions at Yellowstone.
Some of them are
very big.
This one is the most recent, 70,000 years
old and it's called the Pitchstone
Plateau lava flow.
In fact, the size of it is about the size
of Washington DC, and it's about
100 yards thick in most places.
So this is what we're looking at.
We can see volcanic
rocks everywhere, evidence that this is a
really unusual place.
[2:00 minutes] It's a
massive volcano.
What is a Supervolcano?
Some of the eruptions from Yellowstone are
truly enormous eruptions, some of the
largest ones that are know of on Earth.
That includes this green unit here, the Lava
Creek
Tuff, as well as the purple unit which is
the Huckleberry Ridge Tuff which is erupted
2.1
million years ago.
So these are some of the largest eruptions
that we know of on Earth and because they
erupted so much material on the order of about
1000 cubic kilometers
or 250 cubic miles, then they get termed as
"super eruptions," really big eruptions and
the
way that it works, this is kind of a new terminology,
and super eruptions, if you're a
volcano that has exploded and created one
of these deposits, then you get called a
"supervolcano" and that's where the word supervolcano
comes from.
What is a Caldera?
[3:00 minutes] To have this magma that's beneath
the surface and when it erupts and
comes out, there's no longer support for the
ground surface up here, and as a result, the
ground surface just caves in.
It founders and it falls in.
[video of model caldera collapse
made with baking flour] You're left with what's
called a caldera.
It's a subsidence
feature, a cave in feature, that's caused
when it loses its support of the underground
magma.
And as a result, when it first formed, you
had a hole that was on the order of 50
miles long and maybe even 1000, or 2000, or
3000 feet deep in places.
Why are there geysers at Yellowstone?
We have this deep magma chamber and there's
a lot of heat.
The magma is generally at
temperatures like 700-800 degrees centigrade
or something like 12-1300 degrees
Fahrenheit.
There's a lot of heat.
That heat heats up the rock and that rock
then there's
conductive cooling, there's water down there.
[4:00 minutes] That water gets heated up
and so much of the water that's near the surface
at Yellowstone is actually at boiling
temperature and as you go down, it gets hotter
and hotter.
So that creates a pressurized
system of boiling aquifer, boiling groundwater
and that becomes unstable.
[set of
photographs of geysers] It can cause earthquakes
and of course, it causes the thermal
features that we see everywhere at Yellowstone
and that make Yellowstone so famous--
the geysers, the fumeroles, or steam vents,
the hot springs that are so beautiful and
contain so many kinds of life and thermafile
bacteria.
So that's what makes Yellowstone
special and it's pretty much all due to this
underground magma system.
Some other Geologic hazards in Yellowstone
So we have these massive eruptions that are
really quite rare and then we have these lava
flows that happen more frequently but still
not...the last one was 70,000 years ago.
But
this would be a really big event if it happened
again within the park. [5:00 minutes] It
might cause forest fires, it might dam up
rivers, and it would cause a lot of commotion
and anxiety within Yellowstone, but it would
have very little long-range effect.
It
wouldn't affect people in states that are
hundreds of miles away certainly.
We have other
big events that occur at Yellowstone-- for
example, earthquakes.
In 1959, there was a
magnitude 7.5 that occurred out near Headkin
Lake, [photograph of landslide;
photograph of the Tetons] caused a lot of
damage in the park and also caused a lot of
changes to the thermal areas within Yellowstone.
The Teton fault is on the border of the Teton
Mountains south of the Park and it
potentially could have a very big earthquake
associated with it.Beyond that, we have the
hydrothermal explosions or steam explosions
when the
groundwater system becomes too pressurized
and erupts during some sort of a perhaps an
earthquake or due to a change in lake level.
And what happens is that you get the
groundwater system can cause really large
holes in the ground, sometimes hundreds of
feet across.
[6:00 minutes] This is a turbid lake right
here, Indian Pond and Mary Bay.
[photo of blue pond taken from the air] All
of these were created in the last 15,000 years
by explosions of the hydrothermal system.
In this case no magma's erupted, and they're
fairly localized events in terms of their
damage, but they're still definitely relevant
for
what's going on at Yellowstone and need to
be watched.
Almost every year, somewhere in Yellowstone,
there's a small hydrothermal explosion.
Sometimes they may only be a couple feet across,
but we find evidence for them.
Sometimes we see a little bit of smoke coming
out or fumes coming out in a place we
didn't expect it.
Sometimes somebody hears it.
And in lucky cases, we actually get to
witness one of these explosions and that's
happened every few years as well.
We have no
way of predicting these explosions, especially
the small ones, but we hope that as time
goes by, [7:00 minutes] we'll get more and
more knowledge about how they work and
maybe get the chance that some day, we'll
be able to have some predictive capabilities
for these explosions.
[Music playing]
[credits]
Yes!
Yellowstone is a volcano
An unscripted interview, January 2009, 7:00
Minutes
Featuring Jake Lowenstern, Scientist-in-Charge,
Yellowstone Volcano Observatory
Produced by Stephen Wessells
Co-Producer, Dina Venezky
Music, Alon Levitan
For additional information:
http://volcanoes.usgs.gov
http://volcanoes.usgs.gov/yvo/
[graphic of logo: USGS, science for a changing
world]
[end]